[Applause]
heavily so many of you know that I open
my talks with a science lecturer of some
kind or another and today will not be
any different except that this one is
going to require a certain amount of
audience participation and I know how
much we hate audience participation
especially those people who say oh no
that cheer wasn't loud enough yell
louder next time but I'm not going to
ask you to yell the only thing I'm going
to ask you to do is exercise leg muscles
and stand up or sit down at the
appropriate time so please indulge me in
this because I think it will be
educational first of all I would like
everyone to stand up if possible good
good thank you all that was good now
everything else I'm going to be asking
you to do will be easier because I'm
only going to ask you to sit down but
not yet everyone who is not or never has
been a programmer sit down now okay well
that was a failed experiment
everyone is apparently a programmer good
next if you are carrying only one X
chromosome sit down
uh-huh that's right that's right good if
you have two X chromosomes you must
remain standing does anybody see a
problem with this what the devil is
going on that was the end of the
experiment thank you all you can all sit
down now
the title of today's talk is the scribes
oath and I'm going to make the case that
we programmers are the modern-day
scribes we have a secret literacy secret
in the sense that most people don't want
to have it and that literacy is
absolutely essential to the survival of
our society to the operation of our
society we have the hidden knowledge you
and I have the hidden knowledge which is
the glue and lubricant that makes
everything run I want you to consider
the walls of this room
how much software is running in the
walls of this room is there a software
in those speakers there nowadays it is
cheaper to put a little digital signal
processor in there running a little bit
of fast Fourier transform written in C
by some kid in it 2:00 in the morning
than it is to put an inductor and a
capacitor in there to filter out hum is
there software in that exit sign up
there you wouldn't think that an exit
sign a little green picture of a running
man would have software in it but very
likely there's a battery in there and
nowadays we make sure our batteries
state charge by putting little digital
signal processors in them that trickle
charge them so as to eliminate memory
effect think of the road out there how
much software is running in a modern car
anybody know the line count about a
hundred million lines of code in a
modern car that's not a Tesla by the way
alright just a regular old modern car
with a GPS and a sound system and all
that entertainment nonsense in there
hundred million lines of code and that
should scare the devil out of you
because you know what that code looks
like
and of course most of that code is not
controlling anything significant but
some of it some of it controls the
engine some of it controls the
accelerator pedal you know you step on
the accelerator pedal you kind of think
that there's a cable going deep into the
heart of the engine changing a valve
allowing more fuel to go in that's not
the way that works anymore
you kind of hope when you step on the
brake pedal there's a cable it goes over
to the brakes and squeezes the calipers
on the disks that's not the way that
works anymore there's code in there if
statements written by teenagers how many
people have died because of bad code
written in cars they caused the cars to
lose control and that number is not a
trivial number dozens at least and
hundreds have been injured we are
killing people now you and I did not get
into this business to kill people we got
into this business because we walked
into a drugstore one day and there was a
Commodore 64 or or a trs-80 and we knew
a little bit of basic and we wrote an
infinite loop to print it our name
infinitely on the screen until yeah
that's why we're programmers you know
the power the power I can do anything
with this machine we didn't know we were
going to wind up killing people but that
is the state that we live in now we have
the power not quite of life and death
but certainly the responsibility and no
one quite gets this yet right quite with
a couple of close scares recently but
nobody quite yet understands how
intrinsic you and I are to the entire
world but before we go there let's let's
back up a little bit because I want to
look at the history of program
I want to go back in time to the moment
when there was just one programmer this
dude now there were other people who did
programming like things I don't want to
leave out people like the Countess of
Lovelace ADA who was the first person in
history I believe to understand that
computation did not have to involve just
numbers she was the one who had an
insight as she was translating papers of
lectures of Babbage she was the one who
had an insight that numbers could
represent other things than numbers
physical things symbolic things but the
first person to actually write code that
you and I would think of as code that
executed on an electronic computer was
Alan Turing and he wrote this code in
probably 1946 and I'll just skip ahead
of these fly these ones there we go
yes yes he wrote this code in 1946 and
he wrote a paper about it this
interesting problem of writing code and
he made a prediction and I put the
prediction here on the screen it is
perhaps one of the most prescient
predictions of someone of that ilk I've
seen we shall need a great number of
mathematicians of ability because there
will probably be a good deal of this
kind of work to be done do you think
there's a good deal of this kind of work
to be done he was right about that
although I don't think he knew just how
right he was
and notice who he thought he would be
recruiting mathematicians of ability
well at least we all know our X
chromosome count okay
one of our difficulties this is still
Alan Turing right in 1945 one of our
difficulties will be the maintenance of
an appropriate discipline so that we do
not lose track of what we're doing how
did he know how did he know that an
appropriate discipline mathematicians of
ability appropriate discipline yeah that
describes us pretty well I'd say how
many programmers were in the world 1945
the answer is on the order of one Alan
Turing a few other people how many
computers were there in the world at
that time on the order of one there were
a couple a big nasty electronic machines
that were very difficult to work you had
to run the program many times because
the program would fail in the middle
because a truck would Rumble by on the
road and disrupt the the way the machine
worked
those were interesting days but then
came the 50s and in the 50s we had
better technologies you look at core
memory here anything well that's a
better technology yeah that was a better
technology over the CRT memory that they
had before that now memory core memory
is still remarkably expensive does
anybody remember when 64 K was virtually
infinite whose it was yeah okay you
remember that and your hair isn't even
great at or oh you're dying yeah yeah
sorry so I shouldn't have let that out
in the 50s we started producing
computers out of vacuum tubes and the
reason we could do this is that they
started really mass producing vacuum
tubes and getting them to be very
reliable prior to that time vacuum tubes
were not real reliable things they
failed a lot they burned out a lot you
couldn't rely on them if you were going
to use 10,000 of them but in the 50s we
got a little better
that the computers became a little
better this is the era when languages
were developed Fortran for example
anybody write Fortran like Fortran one
oh yeah okay that's good yeah go back
and write a little Fortran one day if
you want an experience in hell
Lisp Lisp was developed during this era
we're still programming in Lisp what is
it about Lisp this is the language that
refuses to die we've tried to kill it
over and over it won't die it just keeps
coming back and back I have a feeling
that it will be the only language to
survive all of you Swift programmers out
there and go programmers and dart
programmers and elixir programmers all
you guys you're all going to be coding
Lisp Wow your children will between 54
and 1960 IBM sold 140 of these machines
think about that over the period of six
years only 140 computers were sold by
IBM these 705 and 709 machines were big
fat ugly machines unreliable but they
were reliable enough for large labs and
they could do hardly anything but by
today's standards but fancy machines for
those days notice who's sitting at the
console there's two x-chromosomes there
and that leads to an interesting issue
anybody know who that is that is Grace
Hopper Grace Hopper was a very early
programmer but more than just a
programmer she was an innovator a
scientist a computer scientist someone
who had profound impact on the
programming community she is the
inventor of the word compiler
she was the first person to ever write a
compiler the very first compiler to be
written was written by Grace Hopper way
the heck back in God knows what years
sometime in the 50s what's called a zero
she was the person who was instrumental
in eventually getting COBOL which we
will forgive her for one day and just to
make sure that you don't think she's an
outlier this is the programming staff of
the ENIAC back in those days men did
hardware and programming was considered
clerical work and so the women could do
that and that was the attitude that
turns out that there were a lot of women
programmers during this period when I
was young 18 and that would have been
1970 I started my career I got my first
job as a programmer and the place I was
working was a kind of insurance company
and at this insurance company there were
perhaps 30 25 30 program or something
like that a third of them on the order
of a third were women and virtually all
of them were in their 30s or 40s these
were not people who were young the way
we think of programmers nowadays I
should do the experiment with the age
demographics but I won't here because
that would be embarrassing many of these
people were older than you and I think
of starting programmers they were more
mature they had experience in business
they understood schedules and deadlines
and that's because they were not drawn
from school they had other jobs before
they became programmers because that's
the only way you could get programmers
in those days there were other people
doing other jobs and then companies
decided well we need somebody to program
these computers and they would draw from
exist
staff I'll make that point in a minute
so by 1960 how many computers are in the
world and the or being the answer is
probably on the order of a hundred or
200 or 300 something like that maybe a
thousand Dominus I'm going to keep it
with the Big O notation of of 1e two
here by 1960 there weren't a lot of
computers in the world
how many programmers were in the world
and the answer to that is fairly
straightforward in those days it took a
fairly large staff to keep one machine
running and the reason for that is that
there was no place to get an operating
system there was no place to download
any code you could not download a
framework they're real frameworks there
were no operating systems except little
tiny kernels and even those little tiny
kernels we often just threw away and
wrote all our own code it was not
uncommon in those days for every single
instruction within the machine to be
written by the programmers local to that
machine if it ran in the computer you
wrote that code so it took a fair number
of programmers to keep a machine running
so we could imagine that the number of
programmers in the world by 1960 was
something on the order of a thousand
maybe one or two or three or 5,000
something like that not much larger by
1960 but then something happened of
course the transistor was invented it
was actually invented long before that
but it became commercially feasible
between the 50s and the 60s and they're
much more reliable within vacuum tubes
and they take a lot less power and
they're a lot smaller and you can cram
them into a much tighter space and they
don't dissipate it nearly as much heat
and so you can make computers much
smaller out of them and because of that
by 1965 IBM had sold 10,000 of these
machines 1401 that's a huge increase in
production over a hundred and twenty and
six
years now we're selling 10,000 in just a
couple of years and they were selling
them well at none I didn't sell them
actually they rented them for $2,500 a
month which in today's dollars would be
around $20,000 this was cheap enough for
many businesses to order them and so we
suddenly found ourselves with lots and
lots of computers the number of
computers in the world was growing
rapidly it was now on the order of ten
thousand maybe more twenty thirty forty
thousand and how many how many
programmers do you need to keep that
many computers alive probably 10 times
that many so maybe there were a hundred
thousand programmers in the world by
1965 this is 20 years after Alan Turing
twenty years two decades and all of a
sudden we've got hundreds of thousands
of programmers and who were these
programmers where did we get them from
well I weren't enough engineers and
scientists and mathematicians out there
to fill the bill and we didn't have CS
grads yet first computer science
graduate program was put together in the
70s so these people had to be drawn from
the Brat best and brightest of current
employees and once again it was a simple
selection process you took the smartest
people in your company and you said
maybe you'd like to program these
computers a new challenge a new kind of
career and the people who came in were
people who a were selected by their
superiors B were competent in in their
some kind of technical ability and C
understood business understood
management understood schedules and
deadlines these were not 22 year-olds
they were generally more mature
though not mathematicians they were
experienced disciplined professionals
and I imagine that Alan Turing would
have approved
to some extent by 1966 IBM was producing
a thousand IBM 360s every month the rate
of production had gone up by yet another
order of magnitude note who's loading
that tape drive up there by 1966 Olli
ohand all Kristian Nygaard had invented
oh oh you know this thing that we do all
the time now that was invented way back
then right back when computers were
scarce and programmers were scarce er
olio and all Kristian Nygaard invented
the technology of object-oriented design
Dijkstra wrote his paper go to
considered armful introducing functional
not functional programming sorry
structured programming giving us what
the first of the paradigms that we have
so eagerly adopted since and in 1968 it
was Ken Thompson and Dennis Ritchie who
gave us C and Unix this was an extremely
prolific period in computer science most
of the stuff that we consider now to be
foundational revolutions in our industry
happened during that ten-year period by
people who did not go through computer
science degrees does it work nee 5 years
later
Digital Equipment Corporation is
producing 50,000 PDP eights all over the
world many computers were starting to
show up from company after company after
company there was a period during this
time when the number of companies
producing many computers was more than a
hundred many computers were just
everywhere and anybody could buy them if
you had a spare 10 thousand dollars
right so people didn't buy them you know
families didn't buy them yet
but companies of any size could buy a
computer at this point
how many computers were in the world by
1970 something on the order of hundreds
of thousands this is 25 years after
touring there are now hundreds of
thousands of computers in the world
how many programmers are in the world
got to be millions by 1970 it has to be
Millions and who are these millions who
are these hundreds of thousands of
people these millions of programmers
writing code me this is when I got
involved 1970 I was 18 years old got a
job at a an insurance company I told you
about that was me at that time but I was
not alone there were lots like me lots
and lots and lots of CS and EE grads and
they all had something in common because
there was a double e program there was a
computer science program in those days
you could now by 1970 begin to graduate
with the idea that you would be a
computer programmer that became feasible
by then and there was something similar
about all these people we were all young
and we were almost all male as I told
you before at my first job there were 24
programmers most in their 30s but some
percentage of them between 30 and 50 % I
don't know the exact count were women
there were a lot of women there but 10
years later I was working at a company
where we had 50 programmers and they
were all in their 20s or early 30s and
three were women something very dramatic
in my experience happened between 1970
and 1980 other people think that the
event occurred in the 80s certainly
there are graphs to show that but my
experience was that it actually began in
the 70s
this exodus of women from our field here
is a graph that shows what happened and
it seems to have this inflection point
in 1985 I don't know why my experience
is so far shifted earlier in time maybe
there's some kind of lag time in this
graph but the Democrat demographics of
programming had decisively shifted
towards young men and remains that day
today that way today
and by the way I don't think touring
would have thought of these young men as
disciplined mathematicians or people of
discipline business had to have
programmers the need the demand was
ferocious and what very young men lack
in discipline they make up for with some
kind of energy and they're cheap I don't
want to tell you what my starting salary
was as a programmer it was not real high
I'll tell you nowadays starting
programming starting starting salaries
for programmers are higher that's good
I'm glad
then I took when I was that age now
remember up to this point whenever you
draw this point programmers were
disciplined professionals they had been
drawn out of previous employers and
employees they understood business and
schedules and what to leave in and what
to leave out but now business was faced
with hordes of very young people massive
numbers those old folks had done all the
met all the miracles
it was those folks those earlier folks
who had given us the virtual memory
operating system and and the space
program and invented things like
structured and functional and
object-oriented programming and giving
us Fortran COBOL and Algol and Lisp and
C in Unix
it was not the hordes of young men who
came later those original programmers
they knew how to get stuff done big
things done even on small computers some
people have said who's doing agile here
by the way I'm sorry I'm asking for more
audience participation who's doing agile
so this is this is you know if I had
asked that question 10 years ago I would
have gotten very close to a nil response
nowadays it's virtually everybody doing
agile of some kind or another now if I
were to define to you what I think
agile is fewer of you would raise your
hands but that doesn't matter to me
right now most of you believe that you
are doing some kind of agile how many of
you are doing scrum virtually the same
number maybe half that's fine we'll talk
about scrum a little later but all right
you're doing scrum or agile or something
like that
in the early days of agile I think it
was Kent back or maybe it was word
Cunningham who said or maybe it was Dave
who said agile is the process used by
discipline professionals observed in the
wild the people who were doing things
earlier agile was the default but hordes
of young testosterone-driven boys need
discipline imposed upon them from above
they need a process some kind of way for
management to keep control of them and
so this was born as anybody ever read
the paper that brought us the waterfall
process yeah Winston Royce's classic
paper which said please don't do this
this is terrible idea but nobody read
the paper they just saw the picture and
thought yeah a great idea
so I have a hypothesis
how many programmers are in the world
today by the 1970s there were millions
where the 80s had to be tens of millions
by the 90s had to be dozens of tens of
millions how many programmers are in the
world today and it depends on if you
count the VBA programmers but if you do
then the number has to be in the
hundreds of millions there's got to be
some crazy wild number of programmers
just look around the room here look at
the number of people packed in to
Brisbane Australia how did we get from
one in 1945 to hundreds of millions in
2016 this is 70 years how did we get
from one to hundreds of millions in 70
years now you can do the math on this if
you want right this has got to be some
kind of exponential growth and
exponential growth has a doubling time
and if you if you if you break that up
and do just a simple analysis you'll
come to the conclusion that the the
number of programmers in the world
doubles every two and a half years I
don't think that's quite true I think
there was a much more rapid period of
growth in the first ten years and then
the rate of growth stabilized at about
once one doubling every five years I
think that's where we're living now the
number of programmers in the world
doubles every five years and there's a
conclusion you can draw if you believe
that which I think the evidence is
pretty clear that there is some kind of
doubling rate like that there's a
conclusion you can draw and the
conclusion is half the programmers in
the world have less than five years
experience and this is true no matter
when you look because it's doubling
every five years so as long as it
doubles every five years half the
programmers in the world have less than
five years experience which leaves our
industry in a state
of Perpetual inexperience we cannot gain
the experience necessary to mature
because we are bringing in people at a
rate that overwhelms the folks who have
been able to gain some experience and
the observed the the wrong observed fact
is that all programmers are young well
know all programmers aren't young you
said well where are all the old people
we're all still here but just never were
very many of us back then this is a
fundamental problem for our industry
it's a fundamental problem for our
society it's a fundamental problem for
the world why not oh yes yes yes good
yes no I'm not going to do that no no no
no no no no ah yes who's heard of night
capital now you have a few of you have
now this disaster occurred probably five
years ago four or five years ago the
upshot was that in 45 minutes this
company lost 450 million dollars they
did that because some poor software guy
did something stupid and couldn't
correct it fast enough and what he did
that was stupid was twofold actually
there's several people who who did this
stupid thing they left some old code
dead code in a system you know how you
do that sometimes you know this code it
never gets executed but you might need
it one day so you leave it in don't
worry it's not getting executed one day
we might want to turn it on wow they
inadvertently turned it on and they did
it in the right way they they actually
repurposed the flag that turned on that
old code and they deleted the old goat
from the software when they repurposed
the flag so they did all that right but
they had a number
servers to load will call that number n
and they loaded n minus-1 they forgot
one server and when that flag was
repurposed most of the servers were
behaving fine but one of them was
executing the old dead code which now
was making really bad trades and they
got a quick call from the SEC saying hey
guys you're doing something crazy and
the programmers made a fundamental wrong
assumption it's the new code that's
malfunctioning and they reloaded the old
machines with the old code but the flag
was still repurposed and it took him a
few minutes to figure that out and in
that time they lost four hundred and
fifty million dollars and that was the
end of that company by the way they got
redo got to purchase by some vultures
later CEO woke up in the morning without
a company just a couple of programmers
one dumb mistake four hundred fifty
million dollars do I need to talk about
the healthcare software in the United
States anybody know the story of the
Obamacare website this is not a
political rant again it doesn't matter
where you stand on the politics of this
issue this was a software failure of
immense magnitude now it begins with a
fundamentally stupid idea a law was
passed that mandated a date for a
software system to be functioning that's
just stupid you can't do that you don't
know when software systems are going to
function no one knows when they are if
you want to hear about that come to my
talk on estimation later today and I'll
talk about you know why you can't know
when a software assistant was going to
actually be running but they made a much
bigger mistake a couple of years later
they turned it on they turned it on now
there had to be people hiding under
their desks going to turning it on man
you know they really shouldn't be
turning it on because you know like the
system is not ready there had to be guys
yeah whoa
run for the hills so why didn't anybody
listen to those guys
now the upshot of that of course was
that the law was very nearly derailed
didn't quite get derailed but it came
that close to law was already tentative
it had succeeded by one vote but it got
that vote and then the President signed
it into law and then we had two years
and then this fiasco happened and there
was this political upwelling and very
nearly took it out we by our errors can
have significant political consequences
we by our errors can cost immense
fortunes what happened to Volkswagen
what happened there does anybody
remember did you were you there when the
not there obviously did you watch on TV
when the CEO of Volkswagen North America
testified before the Congress of the
United States of America and said and I
quote well it was just some programmers
who did this for whatever reason
and yeah I think he was smoking dope at
the time a CEO of a major corporation
blamed software developers for this
fiasco we can be blamed credibly now I
don't think Congress took him seriously
but he was right it was some software
developers who wrote that code there
were software developers who at their
keyboards wrote code if on EPA test
stand then and I don't know how you miss
the significance of that those
programmers frankly should not be
programmers they transgressed a moral
line in line that I will say don't lie
don't lie don't write code that lies
don't write code that is harmful to
society and I'll leave you to figure out
what harmful to society means they cross
some kind of moral line and there ought
to be some way to point at them and say
sorry you can't be programmers anymore
you lose your programming license or
privileges or whatever we don't have a
mechanism like that now many professions
do however there are professions out
there that are significant to society
that can say to you you can no longer do
this job because you transgress some
line this must be coming to us because
we are too significant now
someday some poor software schmuck is
going to do something terrible
maybe it won't be that terrible and tens
of thousands of people will die and the
politicians of the world will do what
they must they will pass laws they will
legislate they will tell us what
languages we can code in what processes
we have to follow what frameworks we can
use they will control us and regulate us
because we're too dangerous I would like
to get there first I would like to be
there before governments do and the way
that other industries have done this the
way that other professions have done
this is to lay out the rules early
doctors for example laid out the rules
early lawyers Wow they make all the
rules it doesn't matter accountants laid
out the rules early and then eventually
government came to them and said hey you
guys need rules and they said well yeah
we got them right here
and government said oh good because we
don't like to do that kind of work so we
have to start laying out the rules and I
have some candidates for you some
possible rules nine of them and I'm
going to walk through them with you I
call this the scribes oath or the
programmers oath and the first one is
real simple
I will not produce harmful code I will
not lie my code will not lie my code
will not will not seek an end that is
counter to society however you want to
interpret this and you may have many
different ways of interpreting this but
somewhere within you there is a more
immoral fiber an ethical set of ethical
principles and this oath says I will not
cross those ethical principles whatever
they happen to be
to the code that I produce will always
be my best work I could have stopped
that one there because I think it says
enough and by the way you would you
would look at that and think anyone
would expect a programmer to have made
such a promise of course the code you
produce will always be your best work
you will always strive to make sure that
what you are producing is the best you
can produce at that time but I added to
it I said I will not knowingly allow
code that is defective either in
behavior or structure to accumulate we
may not be that good at not writing it
most of us will probably write some bad
code within our lifetime but once we
recognize it as such we will not allow
it to accumulate the sin the real sin is
in looking at a software system and
seeing the code and going oh god that's
crap and then leaving it there
three I will produce with each release a
quick sure and repeatable proof that
every element of the code works as it
should now this seems kind of obvious if
you didn't know anything about software
but you were the consumer of software
you would assume that the producers of
that software proved that it worked why
don't we do this some of us might most
of us do not now what is a proof well
there's two kinds of proofs you can use
there's a mathematical proof which I
don't think is physical that Dijkstra
wanted to do mathematical proofs and
over the years it kind of became obvious
that mathematically proving software was
more complicated than writing the
software itself so probably we're not
going to mathematically prove software
but there's another way that you can
prove software correct and it's not
really a proof but it is a demonstration
and
is to do so empirically to write tests
to show that a sequence of experiments
yields results that are consistent with
the software working as it should and
you and I bet our lives on such
experiments every day there is no
mathematical proof that F equals MA for
example and in fact we know that F does
not equal Ma in certain circumstances
and yet we bet our lives on it anytime
we get into a car or an elevator or an
airplane there is no mathematical proof
that Newton's law of gravity is correct
F equals big G m1 m2 over R squared is
not a formal mathematical theorem but it
has enough empirical evidence behind it
that we are perfectly willing to risk
our lives based on that so that is good
enough proof and that is the kind of
proof I'm talking about here the kind of
empirical proof that demonstrates that
you would risk your life on the proper
behavior of this software for I will
make frequent small releases so that I
don't impede the progress of others I
had a good friend of mine and he and I
would would solder together components
down in his basement when we were 16 and
17 years old and the machines that we
were making were things like multipliers
and little computers and and stuff that
was fun to tinker together and his goal
was always this and it drove me nuts he
wanted to finish everything down to the
last coat of paint and then turn it on
and see it work and this made me crazy
because I thought it's not going to work
and never did of course we are involved
in something that is complicated enough
that it requires that we work in small
increments and those small increments
have the added benefit that other people
can interleave their work within those
small increments so that we don't have
to impede someone if you are of the mind
that you're just going to wait until the
last line of code is written and then
you're going to turn it on everybody's
gotta wait for you
if you're the kindnesses I'm gonna get
everything working and then I'll check
it in then everybody's gotta wait for
you or at least do some horrible merge
which is the same thing as waiting for
you
five I will fearless Lee and
relentlessly improve our work at every
opportunity I will never allow it to
degrade the attitude of making
improvements of looking at what you've
produced and making it better humans
make things better with time if you live
in a house you make that house better
with time if you have some kind of
project you make that project better
with time unless it's software with
software we make it worse with time
how is it that we're allowed to do that
how is it that we allow ourselves to
degrade the software that we have
created
we should promise to always improve it
six I will do all that I can to keep the
productivity of myself and others as
high as possible I will do nothing that
decreases that productivity what
decreases productivity slow running
tests slow running builds don't do
things that slow you down don't accept
things that are slow speed everything up
consider it a design challenge to make
everything go faster so that you're not
impeding productivity seven
I will continuously ensure that others
can cover for me and that I can cover
for them we supposedly work on in teams
what happens when a team is moving a
ball down the field and one of the
members goes down one of the players
goes down what do the other team members
do they cover that hole they know how to
play that position they change their
positions on the field so that they can
cover that hole for the guy who went
down they don't leave the hole open what
do we do what if the database guy goes
down does somebody pick up the database
work what if the GUI guy goes down does
somebody pick up the GUI work is there
someone in the organization that can
have you made sure that someone can pick
up your work if you go down it is your
responsibility to make sure that someone
else can take over for you
if you go down which means you probably
cannot spend your programming days
staring at a screen with headphones on
and your back to everybody else that's
not how a team behaves you're probably
going to have to work with each other
and talk to each other and probably even
program with each other go to Woody's
talk on mob programming and then maybe
you can back down off that a step or two
but still eight I will produce estimates
that are honest both in magnitude and
precision there is something we owe to
our to our employers honest assessment
of what we think something is going to
take the time we think something's going
to take I will not make promises without
certainty how many of you have made a
promise without certainty how many of
you when your boss comes to you and says
hey man we really need this to work by
Friday you know can you try
and it's reasonable does it well of
course I'll try do not do that do not
say of course I'll try because the word
try is insulting it implies that you are
not trying and your reaction should be
how dare you come to me and imply that
I'm not trying I'm doing the best I
possibly can
there are no magic beans in my pocket I
can't work this miracle you're asking me
to work you know why you said you would
try really you know why you said that it
was a lie that you were telling in order
to get rid of the person and that's
breaking the first rule 9 last of them I
will never stop learning and improving
my craft software development is one of
those funny industries where we are in
the midst of this constant churn new
things are coming along all the time
that you and I can debate whether any of
these new things are worthwhile and I
have my doubts about that frankly but
they are coming nonetheless and if you
want to stay in this game
you've got to continuously learn on a on
a month by month week by week basis
basis you've got to be attached to that
firehose of new information coming at
you and watching it like crazy because
in our industry when something starts to
become unpopular you never want to ride
down with it there are people down there
and we don't want to talk about them
don't go riding down stay up on these
waves that keep on coming you are
surfing these waves and learn how to hop
from one wave to the next so you can
stay up on your game and with that I'm
going to close my talk thank you all for
your attention
[Applause]